howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talked
about on the show we now have links to
books and articles referenced in recent
podcasts that are available on our
website
we also offer full transcripts go to gym
rut show calm that's gym rut show calm
this is the third in a series of extra
podcasts focusing on the Koba 19 crisis
today's guest we have Bob Reed who is
the co-founder of a very interesting
company called Everest Everest is a
decentralized platform for the for a new
economy incorporating a massively
scalable payment solution a multi
currency wallet and a native biometric
identity system Everest as far as I know
has about the most complete solution out
there and we'll probably talk about that
a little bit but more to the point I've
invited Bob on to talk a little bit
about how best to think about phasing
the deployment of the universal basic
income the ubi that has been at least in
part specified in the relief bill that's
working its way through the US Congress
as we speak and now it's probably not
enough and we'll have to come back to
the well a few times but let's let's get
rolling there Bob and talk about how
should we think about delivering the ubi
to 110 million American households
probably the best place to start is what
do you feel almost all infrastructure of
government or a bank platforms need to
have like what are the essential
elements and the way we thought about it
was we literally modeled off of Estonia
the nation and even Otto har with India
stack in India right like how do you
take you know if you all full government
systems or banking systems and if you
will make them digital now we're coming
along about 15 20 years later after
those guys and were able to
Yuson blockchain technologies along with
some I would say decentralized storage
techniques to actually sort of be a
next-generation of that now in terms of
elements that we consider that are
inherent in all of those are you always
have to have identity at its base level
right says I call identity is the
operating system of any of these systems
you you know are you who you say you are
right and almost everyone around the
world now is arriving at biometrics you
have to have deduplication of you know
the human being right I'm a singular
piece of carbon and that means you can't
just rely on here's my proof of address
from my bank or here's my passport you
got to get to the biometrics the other
piece of the equation is going to be an
account right so you need to be able to
do a wallet in today's vernacular but a
way to actually store value and transfer
in and out associated with that identity
we did something unique at Everest where
we actually made the account in
distributed storage during the cloud so
you actually don't even need a device to
to reach it the other two elements you
need are you need a ledger so something
goes like had a track what's coming in
and out of this account and then you
need to have some sort of you know
currency unit account all right so you
in the case of ubi you know go with
digital fiat like here's a US dollar and
it means a US dollar
those essential elements get you the
basics on how to do a system are you who
you say you are here's an account here's
a way to if you go in and out of that
account and then you're some digital
money now some of the benefits you get
out of doing digital monies you can
program program it right like you can
say here's a dollar but it has to be
spent in the next 30 days right so you
can make a time-bound
right though so like that solves for
what you know the US government tried to
do in 2008 when they said here's a you
know check everyone gets it and turns
out like 60 70 percent of the people
just put it into savings so it didn't
stimulate the economy but if you made it
time-bound well they have to spend the
money you know some other things you can
do is you say oh hey this is programmed
and it can only be redeemed at the
grocery store or the pharmacy for food
and medicine once you can do some things
like that and then ultimately like look
you can actually reach everybody
regardless of if they have a device or
not and you can do it instantaneously so
you you know you can inject liquidity
into the system in minutes instead of
sending out checks or debit cards and
hoping and praying that somebody gets
its turns on their pin okay and you know
doesn't sell it for for drugs behind
7-eleven yeah it sounds great and you
know if we had a Manhattan Project level
of investment we could probably get that
up and running in some period of time
but it seems to me that it would be
dangerous to you know bet the first
implementation of this UVI which we
presumably want to get out in a couple
of weeks and on you know some new
developments and probably a whole bunch
of regulatory issues security audits and
things like that you know I'll tell you
my own suggestion I realize it's fraught
with all the errors and problems that
you brought up but it has the advantage
of being brute force and failsafe - the
inevitable fairly significant losses
around the edges which would be to go
with debit cards and you know basically
scale up something like the Green Dot
system and of course all the big credit
card companies have their own prepaid
systems and of course they're very
expensive that's mostly because they go
down the retail channel where you know
everything is expensive if you push it
through retail but if the government
gave 72 hours for the biggest credit
card companies to bid on sending a debit
card once a month to every American we
could get that up and running
in probably two weeks and we could
actually address what you discussed as
what I call the time to live problem on
the money because it's absolutely key
that if we want this money to be
stimulus it has to get into circulation
and not just put into people's bank
accounts and you and we know that tough
times people want to build up their bank
accounts but even with a debit card you
could say the debit card only lives for
forty-five days I would provide some
overlap each month but make it 45 days
or 60 days and so you get a new debit
card each each month and you have 45 or
60 days to spend that and now of course
you go you still have the know your
customer your identity problem and it is
kind of interesting that in the United
States we do not have a national ID
unlike in some countries like Germany
and France etcetera they're more or less
as a registry of all citizens but we do
have the beginnings of one which is the
vast preponderance of people I don't
know if it's 90 95 % file an IRS return
each year and so you could use that as
the starting point we could then have
banks be authorized to do kyc on people
who aren't in that database and go
through a kyc fraud know your customer
process and basically provisionally
enter them into the same or a parallel
database to the IRS database and then of
course you have to your final group of
people who you know people who are
homeless etc may have no ID band leader
range etc in which case I would suggest
use the existing social welfare agencies
just provide them a stack of cards
knowing there's gonna be some waste and
some fraud and have them pass the cards
out on the street to homeless people
taking a photograph and entering it into
a quick and dirty biometric database
that third part you could not get up and
running in two weeks but the other two
parts you probably could and it would
provide the immediate boost here's the
other key thing about the debit cards I
want to get back to you we talked about
the the electronic methods the beauty of
the debit card is that all the points of
sale already accepted
the hard part is not having to make any
changes at you know a couple of million
points of sale across the economy
everybody takes credit cards and debit
cards anyone who has one of these things
in their hands can literally walk into a
bodega and you know buy you know
whatever the heck they need right on the
spot no questions asked no ID necessary
it's essentially a bearer instrument but
of course that has the downside of fraud
and as you said people you know swapping
them for for beer behind the 7-eleven or
stealing them out of mailboxes and yes
that's true which is why we do need a
better system soon but this has the big
advantage of being failsafe and
deliverable at volume very quickly yeah
I mean oh look I mentioned previously
like if the plane is crashing in all we
have or a world war two parachutes yeah
grab those and get out of the plane
it is brute force and it's costly I
think it's you know what we've seen out
of human behavior and case study after
case study is they will take the money
out of the ATM and then go horde it and
it really won't do much for stimulus and
the other piece you don't get with that
is if you will the the ability of adding
other things so for example how can I
then say here's money just for testing
like here's Co good nineteen testing and
once that testing is done I now want to
be able to store my kovat 19 test
results that I'm positive or negative in
my wallet and so if you will if you if
you have an electronic system that's
based on a biometric system or biometric
ID as I mentioned you end up with
multiple use cases right where you can
actually do medical docs you can do the
state of California wallet inside of
there you can do the US Treasury wallet
inside of there and you can connect to
Wells Fargo and Bank of America - right
it becomes the uber wallet
so that type of infrastructure I mean
look it's it's going to be required
going forward and the only question is
how do we get there
right as I mentioned we modeled after
Estonia so I was actually just chatting
with the ex-president of Estonia who
implemented their system and he was
mentioning like look they're all in
lockdown but every interaction with the
government is electronic and is up and
running and working just fine right now
today right
so they're dealing with kovat 19 in a
system where they you know it's
functioning for them and so sort of
circling back yeah the idea of UVI and
adding liquidity to to the nation
quickly the policymakers are just
dealing with antiquated tools an
infrastructure right like they don't
have four-lane freeways right now
they've got dirt roads and so we're
gonna have to invest and build something
like this yep I absolutely agree I think
the you know context that we could place
us in had another one of these extra
podcasts with Jordan Hall yesterday we
talked quite a bit about the fact that
you know one of the big takeaway lessons
of this event is our society has to be
willing to invest a lot ahead in terms
of resilience and robustness so even if
no single business could have could ever
justify building this thing out it ought
to become a you know social socially
funded program where we have this thing
that you describe and may well be your
system up and running you know for the
next crisis and this is not going to be
the last crisis I can tell you that
between now the end of the the century
so so let's just wargame it a little bit
you know we have our World War Two
parachute
you know scaled up Green Dot plastic
debit cards I know by the way I do
believe we can take care of that ATM
problem but I do think making ATM
withdrawals is an option on these cards
you can make them not available for ATM
withdrawal but nonetheless that will
still be gray market people will buy
beer and trade
for cash and things of that sort if you
turn off the ATM it'll reduce it
significantly so let's say from we use
the World War Two parachute as long as
we need to if there was a truly national
at war level investment in let's say
taking your system scaling it up and
deploying it what's a reasonable period
of time with some fallback failsafe and
testing to be able to actually roll it
out first say for one medium sized state
then a couple of states and then the
whole nation so look we've actually
rolled our system out or tested it in
for example Indonesia like we were given
they had a scenario where they were
handing out the energy subsidy right and
they handed out physical cards and you
were supposed to turn those cards in to
basically get a gas tank to go cook with
it's by the way that's seven billion
dollars distributed to 50 million people
a year okay and what happened there is
well it's one of the biggest black
markets in the world
the vast majority like over 50% of those
vouchers end up with the maids in
Jakarta and it ends up an upper-class so
it just was utterly ineffective and so
we rolled out a way to show you could
send this programmable money only used
by the person attached literally to
their face their biometrics
and they could only redeem it for this
gas tank all right so like we know our
system if you will works right now today
it's proven like we were doing villages
we were out and you know bukittinggi
like you know in in the Netherlands yeah
so what would it take to roll out here
in the US are is eminently scaleable the
issue would be registration right how do
you actually get a user to scan in their
face and scan in their driver's license
for example driver's license by the way
like a it's about 90% of adults you know
age 22
90 you actually have a driver's license
so driver's license actually has your
address and your photo so you can match
your face with that photo and from there
create a wallet so that would be the the
way to that would be the only impediment
to scaling would be how long does it
take to register it's gonna go full
Manhattan Project you do it at the post
offices and the grocery stores and you
register everybody as they walk in and
out right you written you come into the
post office or go to your grocery store
scan your face and your driver's license
on the tablet and boom you're entered
and you now have a wallet that's
connected to the theft net for example
or the government how about the other
half of which I you know alluded to on
you know where the debit cards are so
useful point-of-sale how do you get
these systems you know someone walks
into the bodega and they need to buy
half gallon of milk and two loaves of
bread how does the bodega get set up to
be able to accept this so there's a
couple of different ways so if they're
already doing for example NFC point of
sales which the vast majority are and
you have a smartphone you can literally
take your digital US dollar for
groceries and scan it just like you're
doing Apple pay or you know Google
Wallet right do that today
what's the penetration on the truthfully
I'm laggard I tend to use folding cash
or worst case at credit cards
what's the penetration on things like
Apple pay or Google pay I'm the ability
at the point-of-sale point-of-sale is
actually pretty ubiquitous I believe is
there isn't as much on the smartphone
penetration that is we all hang around
with each other and I'll have super
smartphones truth is on the planet
there's like four to five billion people
that don't have smart phones out of the
seven and a half that exists today so
Americans that I have a higher
penetration of smartphone but there's
still a good you know good percentage
that don't and so as I mentioned before
like we can actually give you a wallet
up in the cloud so you don't need a
device at all now in that case for point
of sale for example in the grocery store
right where you registered
you could scan your face put in your
pin and have it spit out a QR code
that's good for the money
right and that QR code can be scanned at
you know at the register mmm okay I like
that I like yeah you say like the other
ways like look if you just simply walk
in and the point-of-sale has a camera or
the clerk has a camera like a smartphone
that's the point of sale - or why
suppose people like the square payment
system could augment their system with a
camera and then hook back to your do the
biometric processing you know call your
database and then connect to the ledger
and the wallet and again if you
partnered with people who have that is
inexpensive and you know massively
scalable point of sale devices then that
would take care particularly the little
guy I mean the big guys they'll figure
it out but I'm worrying about the moms
and pops right the auto mechanics and
the bodegas etc just need a smartphone
maybe they can if you'll I could walk in
with my wallet on my phone and say
here's a payment and just literally go
peer-to-peer and it runs across our
rails to actually ledger the transaction
out of my walton into theirs and now
what's the error rate both the you know
the false negatives and the false
positives because it would be mighty
annoying if let's say you're a poor
person without a smartphone you go down
to the grocery to buy some stuff for
your kids you know you have money in
your wallet they scan you but the
biometrics doesn't match
that's actually pretty solvable at scale
we've seen across the planet it's not
that as hard as it used to be I'm gonna
give you a very real sense with our own
government so Global Entry right when
you come in to the airports from
overseas used to do for fingerprints and
then take a picture of yourself and in
the last six months they've phased out
the fingerprints and literally just gone
with face so they do face and then they
look at the name of the person that came
in on the on your airline ticket and
that is deduplication at a 99
point something percent it's it's
working well enough literally for our
own borders and then DHS is deadly
serious about this stuff yeah even 99%
it would be considerably better than the
leakage you'd expect from a plastic
debit card system yeah and by the way
that's just biometrics as soon as I say
it's you know my name attached to that
biometrics then you're at 99 point
something okay so it sounds like the
technology is there very interesting
pretty commoditized now everyone's
shooting at the 98 99 percent so let's
go back to my original question let's
say that resources were unlimited
somehow we actually got a political and
regulatory decision to go do
this right we know that's not gonna be
easy let's say we did and someone said
here is essentially a blank check and
how long is gonna take including
spinning up the registration process
well what's a safe number is it a year
nine months two years what would you say
if someone literally tapped you on the
shoulder and said okay Bob we've vetted
your we believe it'll scale but
whatever it takes do it we're in the
neighborhood of months and the you know
hesitation we'll hear in my voice is if
you will testing right so it's okay like
sure we can all go here's hundreds or
thousands of tablets let's go ahead and
run the city of San Diego or let's go
ahead and do the US military for example
as the you know the beta test let's call
it you know weeks then in terms of
registering everybody and then you would
literally then have to do transactions
after transactions to if you will make
sure everything's robust so blank check
we're in the neighborhood of months in
terms of getting it to a position where
you know we can show provable everything
at scale and that does not necessarily
include the spin-up of registration no
that would be registration like you'd
pick a select population like I said
here's the you just a city or the US
military and we're dealing with hundreds
of thousands
of people or san diego's two million and
you could literally have all of those
people filing in a few weeks register
get their accounts and then start
sending money to them or having them
transact absolutely any is just thinking
out loud here I know this adds or
subtracts but you know let's say we want
to do it in parallel while you're doing
the regional test at a national level we
could recruit a whole core of notaries
essentially people who are vetted and
are given you know upscale devices and
anyone that comes to that notary could
be registered by the notary right today
so in Indonesia when we rolled out we
didn't have foundational identity that
is a government ID mm-hmm
we were dealing in the poor
neighborhoods and they had a family card
and in that case we literally had to
have Bri Bank agents and sometimes
government overseers to actually act as
notaries to register people now in the
case of the US where we're dealing with
90 some percent that have foundational
identity you can literally do self
registration at home you scan your
driver's license scan your face and boom
you're off to the races yeah that work
for up seventy-five percent of people
keep in mind that yeah amazing number of
Americans are totally computer
illiterate but seventy five percent so
could play start and then have the
notaries have banks you have a layers of
backup at the end of the day you know
social welfare agencies that go out and
register people on the streets right now
what's interesting is I mean going back
to what you were saying before is all of
this does rely on it has to have a
common identity batplane that is I can't
register myself with my driver's license
in one area and then go to social
welfare and get my biometrics there and
then go to a third spot and say here's
my proof of address because I've got a
letter from a bank those end up with
three different identities and so this
is why we always drive towards you have
to have deduplication which is
biometrics and if you have a common
identity system underneath all of them
then you've got a system that will
actually not be rife with fraud right
and you'll actually be yeah you know
like I said fundamentally are you who
you say you are and is this account
attached to you as a singular human
being yep and yeah that would if
assuming that you that the the base
layer biometrics is indeed 99 plus
percent
it makes fraud not worth doing right you
know that's the interesting about crime
you don't have to have a bulletproof
system to stop crime just have to make
it such that it's it mostly doesn't work
and the the risk for getting caught are
pretty damn high right right and again
as part of this I would make a really
draconian laws I would say this is
wartime anyone who attempts to defraud
this system as an individual is gonna
get ten years in the slammer anyone who
gets it's doing it an organized crime
fashion life without parole asshole
I mean this is life and during wartime
we should not tolerate anybody
attempting to defraud the system right I
agree yeah you know the other thing
that's sort of interesting along these
lines as we delve into like okay how can
you actually implement this is actually
understanding who owns and controls
everything and if you I think that
Europeans have been you know probably
the most forward thinking on this in
terms of GDP are in terms of if you will
right to be forgotten and the identity
is actually the users so fuel in that
natural social construct of the
government saying I will give you
something but tell me something about
you right and the citizen has the right
to say no and they don't get the benefit
or they have the right to say yes and
they should have the right to go here's
my I can verify I mean so here's a
biometric like verification but you
don't have to give the biometrics to the
government you just have to verify that
you really are the guy attached to this
thing and here's my name and address and
I'm an American for example but for
example my bank balance in my health
records probably aren't part of
the social exchange of ubi right
actually take it back like bank balance
probably is like if I make too much
money I'm probably not eligible but
health records in my Instagram account
certainly are not part of that exchange
and so you need to architect an identity
system that allows privacy for the user
and granular sharing of whatever the
social contract dictates nice I like
that a lot
that's a beautiful architecture because
certainly most people will be willing to
share a fair amount and return for the
ubi
but not everything while other things
like you know to validate my Roku box or
something you know I'm not gonna give
them a damn thing except my pseudo
anonymous ID that's attached to a
payment mechanism yeah you say like look
pseudonymity doesn't work for financial
transactions as you know Facebook's
Libre Association found out you know
very quickly with every financial
regulator and every central bank in the
world saying no that's a money
laundering all right bye wait dig a
layer deeper on the identity piece it's
it's important that sort of in the 21st
century we need to think in those 21st
century terms everyone's used to a
database right and that's just because
historically that's all we had it's
important that you architect a system
that actually is not a centralized
database that's owned by somebody or
some organization right you need to
architect it so that literally the user
actually has the keys and literally not
even I or Everest or the government
actually has the keys
that's dangerous I mean you know we've
looked at this a lot and one of the
advantages of things like you know
standard American credit cards is that
transactions can be reversed
you know there's when people lose their
credentials there's a soft way to get
them back
you know the private key signature world
of blockchain has some real downsides
yeah if your transactions are different
than if you will identity key holding
so I'll give you a sense the way we
architected the identity if you we've
got a couple blockchain so our identity
blockchain is really just about key
holding which is who can get in and see
Jim's account balance or his biometrics
or whomever and that just comes down to
does you know does ever hold the keys of
the US Fed hold the keys whose and we
made it so that literally we distributed
the keys so that no single entity can
open your identity data store so that's
one element on just identity on the
transactions yeah of course you have to
architect in travel rule for example
like you have to be able to stop a
transaction and freeze an account and so
that's literally why we did a second
transaction ledger where you can
actually track what account is doing
what activity and freeze it if you have
to does that make sense yeah basically
you layer services on top of the base
identity so you could essentially layer
in a series of services that say exactly
emulated American Express yeah for
instance I I use American Express
exclusively for all my online
transactions because they're great you
call him up and say don't pay that
asshole right he me right he
wouldn't take it back and he said we
wouldn't take back a broken item when he
said he would don't pay him and American
Express just doesn't pay him right but
the other piece you get by separating
the identity from the transaction is you
get if you will you can't collect a
bunch of metadata on transactions and
find out stuff about the person that
probably isn't legal or appropriate
right because you've separated like
here's my UV I exchange like here's my I
can verify me here's my I prove American
and I'm at this income level that's
great that's one transaction if I go to
my health provider I can do the same
thing I can say here's my identity and I
will share my health record for two
hours with this doctor it's a separate
transaction in which case you can't look
at the two separate transactions and
come back and say oh this is Bob he's
clearly taking his money to go to the
doctor right the separation between the
two actually creates a level of privacy
I think that's it's important in
practice I like this I think you guys
have done some very innovative thinking
here in separating this or the values
and layers of service yet provide the
ability to build privacy where necessary
yeah we're necessarily I mean look if
you're gonna do an interaction with the
government they're gonna know you know
here's the service here's the
information we need to do this service
and we know who you are and that's the
way it goes we won't take money yeah
that's what goes right if you don't want
it don't give it don't don't ask for it
right yeah you send over a thousand
dollars from here to the Philippines
you got a produce source of wealth
source of funds where is it going
etc etc and that's the you know as I
call it the social contract that's also
the social contracts are laws so we just
map in what the law is into you know
digital to make it easier and more
transparent well right Bob this is great
very well-thought-out
and before we wrap up here and we are
trying to keep these extra episodes much
shorter than our usual ones what's it
take to get this done I mean it sounds
like you guys we've done a lot of
thinking you got the system ready to go
with significant funding you could
deploy it in months let's you know being
a former manager of technology I take
whatever the damn techies tell me to
double it so let's say the end of the
year right who has to make the decision
and how do we get them to make the
decision oh boy that's the billion
dollar question isn't it literally right
yeah it might be the trillion dollar
question so our system is ready to go
with scales like its cloud-based so
anything digital and cloud like we could
literally run millions of transactions
no problem it really will be how do we
get to the decision-makers and actually
get the relevant stakeholders in the
same room right you're gonna have the
privacy advocates you're gonna have the
Fed you're gonna have US Treasury you're
gonna have all sorts of folks that
actually want to apply on how to
actually get this out and getting to
those people well that's about half my
day the last
two weeks you talk to minuchin yet not
yet
let's see the guy I think it's gonna be
somewhere between him or Jerome at the
Fed the way we approach this is we work
with organizations that actually can
move a million to a hundred million
people with a key if you will
application so ubi would be a great
application now once it's done CDC or
Department of Health or Department of
Labor or state of California or Virginia
could write on top of what they've
already done because you've got verified
identities with wallets with a way to
transact
so whoever drun you know the question
what what does the killer app and who is
the decision-making body to drive the
first implementation and so it very well
might end up being Gavin up in
Sacramento right he very well has the
appetite and the budget to actually go
out and do California properly and get
robust systems in place so that
California is ready for you know the
next wave but the real answer if we
wanted to have it done for this
particular crisis and oh by the way it's
possible we won't need it but again as
we Jordan tonight Jordan Hall and I
discussed yesterday part of building a
robust and resilient society is making
medium-sized bets that you might have to
throw away let's say it turns out
magically we solve this epidemic in
September long before we need to
continue having ubi next year we have to
throw away a few billion dollars oh well
all right
that would be my view on it in terms of
how a society ought to think about
hedging its bets its interests
I'm actually not seeing it exactly the
same way and I'll give you some concrete
examples of why not which is the
Estonian experience was literally driven
by the banks the banks got tired of
paying for know your customer systems
and so they went to the government said
give me a national ID system where I can
actually just kyc everybody well as soon
as they did that then the government
looked up and went well gosh now I can
deliver like seven government services
over the same infrastructure India did
the same thing it's like let's put a
billion one
with biometric identity into the system
and then build some rails so now they're
doing pensions there now this is the way
you said it for a bank account this is
the way you do you know do ten other
things in society and so you know we're
seeing other societies leapfrog ahead
you know and I think the Americans just
need to catch up
so the will have to invest in in this
infrastructure and the only question is
what are the 10 or 3 or 30 applications
that ride on top of the new
infrastructure yeah you're right
you're right I was wrong if we build
this thing for kovat and we don't need
it we still have a hugely valuable asset
for our whole society to make use of
yeah absolutely
all right Bob this has been amazingly
interesting anybody who knows how to get
to minutiae
contact Bob at is you know young I think
you can probably find out to get hold of
them at Everest dot org we need to get
Bob sitting down with minuchin or the
guys at the Fed we need to get this done
goddamn it
that's right hi Jim all right thanks Bob
this has been remarkably interesting and
I think our listeners will find it you
know important and we're thinking about
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
Jared Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]